[Music]
Welcome to this 2025 release wave 2
business central launch edition. This
session is about document reporting and
my name is Kenny Pontop. I'll be your
host and with me I have Mirao.
>> Hi, I'm MO. I'm part of the engineering
team and today I'm very excited to show
you how we made world layouts easier and
better for everybody.
>> Awesome. So I am looking so much forward
to seeing the demos from Miracle. Just
to give some context, in the past years
the experience to add data to document
layouts in Word was, let's say,
complicated, but not anymore. In this
wave, we introducing a new um experience
in the Word addin so that any power user
or consultant with a few actions can add
data to the layout. This makes the setup
way quicker. Uh, it boosts productivity
and it helps you get those customized
layouts out to customers and
stakeholders faster.
Let's see the new data experience in
action. Sure. Let's start from the
report layouts page. Here I already
filter by the type so that we can only
focus on word layouts. But before
jumping into Word and show you how you
can edit the layout with a new word
addin, let me show you how it looks.
Let's take for example the customer
order or the summary, the very first
one. And let's see what the report looks
like.
All right, as we can see, it's a very
simple one. It's showing it's iterating
through different uh customers and
different orders. So now let's move and
see how we can create new layouts with a
new data picker. The first thing that I
want to make sure is to export the
layouts. Making sure that all the custom
XML parts are included. And to do that,
I can simply click on update and export
layout.
Now, let's go to Word. So, as you can
see here, we have our layout. And in my
word tab, I have a new uh business
central preview.
If I click here, this is the new version
of the word addin. As we can see, we
have a new data control section which
provides an add data action. When I
click on this action, I open a task pane
on the right which is what we call data
picker. And here we can see this tree
structure which basically showcase the
data sets behind the report. And then
here we can expand, we can collapse, we
can look the labels and the report
informations. So now let's say that we
want to create a new table but with a
new data picker. Let me show you how we
can do that. Well, let's start very
simple and create a table which is a
very simple one 2 by two columns. And
the first thing I would like to do is to
to add some labels. Let's say that we
want to show the customer number. And if
I want to do that, all I need to do is
to find the customer number and choose
add field.
That's it. Here we can see now that this
inserted the content controls with both
the text and the tag equal to the field
that we are adding. So in a similar way
I'm going to add here the customer name.
And now I'm actually ready to insert and
repeat over the different customers. Let
me show you how you can do that. Well,
first I want to select the different
rows and columns where I'm iterating.
And now I can expand the data section.
In this case I would like to iterate
through the saline buffer uh here. And
all I need to do is again choose the add
repeater. This time it's a repeater. So
that helps us on understanding what we
are adding. And when I click I can see
that now we have a new content control.
We can clearly see that this time it's a
repeater because now we are providing
that information in the tag to make to
make it easier to understand uh the
layout. And now I'm ready to insert the
data fields that I want to show. So in
this case I will choose the customer
number and then again simply add field
and finally the customer name.
Add field again. That's it. Now I can
save and we can go back to um our
business central environment. I will
create a new layout for this report.
Let's call it data picker. Just give it
a very uh significant name word.
I choose my new layout.
And now let me render it once so that we
can see that all works as expected. And
there you go. Here we have the new table
with the customer number, the customer
name, and the the repeater iterated
through all the different customers.
>> Awesome. That's really easy, BCO. I I
like that. Um, we probably want to add
even more productivity features to the
word addin so that it's even easier, but
we just started with the data parts.
Perfect. Now, um, I saw that you had
this new addin installed. Um, how could
a user like any word user uh, can any
word user just install this?
>> Yes, of course. It's actually pretty
simple. Let me show you how we can do
that. All right. So, when we are on the
homepage of Word, we can add a new addin
in a couple of ways. The most simple one
is to simply come on the home tab here,
addins, and this expands this uh new
popup. We can either search in the
search bar or we can click, we can
choose more add-ins, and this opens up
the app source uh window here. All I
need to do is to type and search for
Business Central. Here you might see
more versions of the Business Central
addin. What you need to make sure is
that you choose the one with the
description that mention the AD data
controls. That's because we have
different versions. So in this case, I
want to choose the second one. And all I
need to do is to choose add.
At this point, words install the addin.
And as you can see now I have my new
business central addin the latest
version with the data controls section
>> and mu you mentioned that what if I
don't have that menu
uh thing uh in the top are other ways to
get the addin
>> yes of course so if you don't see this
one you can also come on file and go
into your account and from here you will
be able to find again the get addins and
when you choose this one again it will
open the apps source window.
>> Awesome.
So, um that's amazing. Like click once
adding data and almost click once to get
the addin. So, what's coming next in
this space? Well, very soon. We didn't
get it in for the demo here for the
recording, but hopefully we'll soon be
able to have it in some update in
version 27 here in the fall. We are
adding tool tips to um to the addin. If
you also watch the server and database
session, we mentioned in there that we
added support for tool tips on data item
fields. Um and this is what we use in
the addin to also make these data sets
um more usable because with the new data
picker we also moving the experience
from a developer towards a more power
user at the customer side. So of course
we want uh people who are not developer
focused to get some help is in what they
add
later and this is not in in 27 but uh
now we are starting to to get
productivity into word addin for real uh
you will likely see more productivity
features coming to make it even easier
to work to to work with word layouts.
There will also be something we call
project seoia. It's a code name for some
very secret projects. Uh we do have an
office hour here in the fall. So in the
in the video uh description, you can
find a link if you want to learn more
about project sequa. But I can tease a
little bit. It's about uh replacing most
if not all of the document layouts in
Business Central towards using Word.
If you want to learn more about uh words
layouts and how to work with them, uh
the easiest is to go to aka.ms/bc
developer. That's our developer guide in
in Microsoft learn. And I showed here on
the picture there's a few navigations
you need to take or simply just search
for how to lay out your report with word
layouts. There's a ton of documentation
of on how you do things with Word. If
especially if you come from a world of
RDL, the old way of doing layouts, you
might need to to get your learning on.
That's it. Just a few uh central
business central resources if if you're
new to this. Um bcall aka.ms/bcall
is the like the landing page for all our
aka links. Um if you have questions as a
partner the aka link aka.ms/bc
yammer will take you to the yammer site
where we discuss everything where
customers are not listening. So if
you're a customer you're not allowed to
be there or you won't be there. um
office hours. I mentioned that uh for
the project SEOA there's also an AKA
link for that. Uh since you're watching
this on YouTube, you might already know
our YouTube channel. The AKA link uh
here for BC YouTube is an easy way to
navigate to the channel. Similarly, we
are very active on LinkedIn. So uh the
aka link for LinkedIn takes you to our
uh LinkedIn account and you should
definitely follow us there to get the
latest updates whenever they are fresh
to publish. Um finally um if you are a
Business Central partner um go check out
the partner portal and learn more about
uh all the resources that are available
there. And with that I think Mo and I
are done. Should we wave to the to the
to the customers? Of course. Yeah.
>> Bye. Thank you.
>> Bye.